Finding Aid for Alan B. Howes papers, 1940-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alan B. Howes papers
1940-2006
Howes, Alan B.
2011112 Aa 2
Alan B. Howes was professor of English at the University of Michigan from 1955 to 2001. He was involved in the formation of several unique programs, such as the NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers, the New England Literature Program, and the Professional Semester. This collection includes correspondence, material from Howes' teaching career and involvement with these programs, and an assortment of Howes' writings.
1.7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Lydie Howes in November 2010 (Donor no. 10455 ).
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Alan B. Howes was born in St. Johnsbury, Vermont on September 20, 1920. He attended high school at Burr and Burton Seminary in Manchester, Vermont, graduating in 1937. He earned his Bachelor of Arts and Master of Arts degrees in American Literature from Middlebury College in Middlebury, Vermont in 1941 and 1943, respectively. In 1945 he was drafted into the U.S. Army and attended the Army Specialized Training Program at Yale from 1945 to 1946. Howes served two years in Japan, the first with the Army and the second with the Civil Service as Chief of the Public Information Office of the Legal Section, SCAP. Returning to Yale in 1948, he began doctorate work in English. While his doctorate work was not yet finished, he taught at the University of Connecticut and as a guest professor from 1951 to 1953 at the Kamakura Branch of Yokohama National University. Howes received his PhD from Yale in 1955. His dissertation was entitled, "Laurence Sterne's Literary Reputation in England," and was published as "Yorick and the Critics" by Yale University Press and reprinted by Archon Books in 1971.
Howes joined the University of Michigan faculty in the Department of English as instructor in 1955 and became a full professor in 1969. Titles of courses taught include Gothic Myth in Literature and Film, Madness in Literature, Freshman Writing and Literature, Evil in Literature and Film, British-American Literature 1600-1830, History of the Novel to 1850, and Changing Attitudes Toward Nature. His teaching career at the university continued until 2001, when he retired at age 80.
Howes was particularly interested in training current and future English teachers, an interest that led to his involvement with the NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers and the Professional Semester. The NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers was a joint program between the University of Michigan and the Southfield School System and sought to improve the teaching skills of English teachers, particularly at the high school level, while giving the University of Michigan Department of English a body of experience helpful in refining its programs for the training of future teachers. About half of the participants were from the Southfield School System, while the other half came from schools across the country. Howes worked with the School of Education to create the Professional Semester in 1974. The Professional Semester's goal was to "teach students how to teach high school" and it combined practical and theoretical aspects of teaching (Robboy and Shaw Michigan Daily, November 23, 1988, in Professional Semester-News Clippings folder). Enrolled students would normally meet for 14 hours a week, except for five weeks in the middle of the term, when the weekly hours would be cut to six or eight and they would spend 60 hours observing classes in local schools. Student involvement in planning was a major aspect of the program. The Professional Semester was an alternative way to satisfy most of the requirements for the secondary teaching certificate in English as it met requirements for a course in language, a course in composition, a course in the teaching of English, observation in the schools, and three "multicultural courses" incorporating ethnic or non-Western cultural materials (from paper on Professional Semester in Professional Semester-Program Description and History folder).
Howes' most noteworthy achievement was probably his role as cofounder and teacher of the New England Literature Program (NELP) from 1975-1990, after which he continued to serve as guest lecturer. This program was created to allow UM students and staff to study New England authors and poets such as Hawthorne, Emerson, Dickinson, Frost and Thoreau in the environment in which their works were created and to experiment with their own writing in journals. NELP was held every year for six weeks in May and June on the shores of New Hampshire's Lake Winnipesaukee and included excursions such as hikes on local mountains and trips to the Maine seashore. Students participating in NELP earned eight academic credits.
The Alan B. Howes Papers document Howes' career in teaching, primarily his many years as professor of English at the University of Michigan, and his involvement in programs such as the NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers, the Professional Semester, and the New England Literature Program (NELP). The records are arranged into nine series: Biographical, Correspondence, Course Materials The Michigan English Teacher, NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers, New England Literature Program, Photos, Professional Semester, and Projects and Papers.
Subjects:
Howes, Alan B.; English teachers--Training of.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. New England Literature Program.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series includes Howes' Curriculum Vitae, an obituary, an award for outstanding teaching presented by the University of Michigan Course Evaluation Committee, and personal academic records.
  - Curriculum Vitae, c. late, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Obituary, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Outstanding Teaching Award, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Personal Academic Records, 1950 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes Howes' communication with students, colleagues, administration, and publishers. Of particular note is correspondence between Howes and publishers concerning permission to reprint various publications to be used in his volume of criticism of Laurence Sterne, a part of Routledge & Kegan Paul's Critical Heritage Series. Correspondence concerning the New England Literature Program and Professional Semester are filed separately in the respective series.
  - General, 1949-1998 (Box 1)
  - Recommendation Requests, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - Reprint Permission Letters, 1966-1973 (Box 1)
  - Rutledge and Kegan Paul, 1966-1974 (Box 1)
- Course Materials
  The Course Materials series includes student course evaluations; an English Composition coursepack prepared by Howes; and examinations, questions, writing assignments, syllabi, and reading lists from various courses. This series gives a sense of Howes' teaching methods and style in his almost fifty-year career as a professor.
  - Course Evaluations, 1982-1999 (Box 1)
  - English 24c English Composition Coursepack, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Exams, 1956-2000; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Questions/Writing Assignments, undated (Box 1)
  - Syllabi and Reading Lists, 1964-2001 (Box 1)
- The Michigan English Teacher
  The Michigan English Teacher series contains seven 1964 and 1965 issues from this serial published by the Michigan Council of Teachers of English. Issues include announcements, reflections, writings, and advice by and for Michigan English teachers. Howes served as managing editor.
  - 7 issues, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
- NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers
  The NDEA Summer Institute for English Teachers series includes mostly administrative material on the program. Among this are two Final Technical Reports authored by Howes providing an evaluation of that year's iteration of the program. The series also includes plans and proposals for the program as well as a participant questionnaire designed to give feedback on its strengths and weaknesses. There is also a set of class rosters, listing participants' names and addresses.
  - Final Technical Reports
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
  - Plans, Proposals, Reflections, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Questionnaire, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Rosters, 1968-1978 (Box 1)
- New England Literature Program
  - Calendars, Schedules, Reading Lists, circa 1980-2003 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987-2006 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation Forms and Summaries, 1982-2000; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Journal Anthologies, 1979-2000 (Box 2)
  - Journal Entries, 1975-1986; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1983-2000 (Box 2)
  - News Clippings, 1975-1987 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Program Description and History, 1985-2001 (Box 2)
  - Program Information Guides, 1996-2006 (Box 2)
  - Rosters, 1977-2003 (Box 2)
  - Staff Manual, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Student Writings, 1980-1986; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Thirtieth Anniversary Celebration, 2004 (Box 2)
- Photos
  The Photos series contains photographs of Howes in Japan circa 1950.
  - Howes in Japan, c. late 1940s-early, 1950s (Box 2)
- Professional Semester
  Among material in the Professional Semester series are correspondence, examinations, student journals, program history, rosters, newsletters, and syllabi. Correspondence includes notices to enrolled students concerning program expectations as well as student letters to Howes reflecting on their experiences. Student journals include students' analysis of their observations at local schools, a requirement of the program. The Segue newsletters were developed by the Professional Semester class of 1988, as a way to keep in touch. They contain updates from that year's participants.
  - Correspondence, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
  - Exams, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - News Clippings, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Observations Journals, 1977-1989 (Box 2)
  - Program Description and History, undated (Box 2)
  - Rosters, 1978-1991 (Box 2)
  - Segue Newsletters, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Syllabi/Reading lists, 1981-1995 (Box 2)
- Projects and Papers
  The Projects and Papers series includes a selection of Howes' writings and information on his research work, including Ph.D. materials and grant/fellowship applications. This series is divided into two subseries: Student and Postgraduate and Professional. The Student subseries includes a variety of papers from English courses during Howes' time as a student at Middlebury College as well as approval for his Ph.D. candidacy and a report on his dissertation at Yale. The Postgraduate and Professional subseries contains Howes' writings while he was a faculty member, most at the University of Michigan, but several at Yokohama National University in Japan. While some of these writings are literary criticism and analysis, others focus on the teaching of English and ways in which it can be improved. Also contained in this subseries are Howes' applications for research grants and fellowships
  - Student
    - “Analysis of An Irish Airman Foresees his Death,” c. early, 1940s (Box 2)
    - “Blake and Ulysses,”, 1940s (Box 2)
    - “The Character of Pilar,”, early 1940s (Box 2)
    - Essay on T.S. Eliot’s “A Cooking Egg,”, early 1940s (Box 2)
    - “From The Life of Johnson,”, early 1940s (Box 2)
    - Literary Criticism Course Papers, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Ph.D. Material, 1949-circa 1955 (Box 2)
    - “The Symbol of the Rose in Yeats’ Early Poetry,”, early 1940s (Box 2)
    - “The Use of Horror in Sanctuary,”, early 1940s (Box 2)
  - Postgraduate and Professional
    - “Beyond Accountability in English,”, undated (Box 2)
    - “Expectation and Surprise in Childhood’s End,”, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Grant/Fellowship Applications, 1957-1961 (Box 2)
    - “Intensive English Conversation -- Volume Two,”, 1953 (Box 2)
    - “Language and Reflection: An Integrated Approach to Teaching English,”, 1991 (Box 2)
    - “Laurence Sterne, Rabelais and Cervantes: The Two Kinds of Laughter in Tristram Shandy,”, 1984 (Box 2)
    - “Learning in the English Classroom -- a Process, not a Product,”, undated (Box 2)
    - “A Linguistic Analogy in Literary Criticism,”, 1965 (Box 2)
    - “The Special Case of Tragedy,”, undated (Box 2)
    - “A Study of Achievement in English Composition in the Senior Class of 1960”, circa 1960 (Box 2)
    - “Walt Whitman’s Chanting the Square Deific,”, 1953 (Box 2)